Thomas W. Amsden Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Thomas W. Amsden Archives
1942-1947
IPAR.001050
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
5
The archives of Thomas W. Amsden including maps, field notes and photographs. These focus on his 1947 Yale dissertation, "Stratigraphy and paleontology of the Brownsport Silurian of western Tennessee."
Amsden, Thomas William
Biographical Sketch
Thomas W Amsden was born January 31, 1915 in Wichita, KS. After getting a B.S. from Wichita State University in 1939, Tom went on to the University of Iowa and studied under Arthur K. Miller. He received his M.S. in 1941. In 1940 Amsden married Virginia McCoy. He has two children, Thomas and Kathy (although he reportedly wished to name them 'Pentamerus siluricus' and 'Dictyonella devonica'). He worked under Carl Dunbar and studied the Brownsport Formation of western Tennessee. He received his PhD in Geology from Yale University in 1947. He taught paleontology at Johns Hopkins University from 1947-1955, and spent much of this time collaborating with G. Arthur Cooper at the U.S. National Museum. From 1955 to 1985, Amsden worked for the Oklahoma Geological Survey out of Norman, OK. He received the Paleontological Society Medal in 1989. He passed away in February 2000.
Description of the Material
Includes Amsden's 1942 field notebooks, in addition to a number of topographic maps, planimetric maps, geologic maps, stratigraphic sections, and photographs of specimens.
Tennessee; Connecticut; Locality information; Field notebooks; Maps; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Maps, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Topographic, Geologic and Planimetric maps.
  - Geologic Maps. Geologic maps of Tennessee., 001056
    - Geologic map. Waynesboro, TN 7.5 Quad., Geology of (1: 125000). U.S. Geological Survey: Geologic., 001586
  - Planimetric Maps. Planimetric maps of Tennessee., 001055
    - Planimetric map. Index Map of Planimentric Maps - Tennessee (1: 1000000). U.S. Geological Survey: Planimetric., 1937; 001552
    - Planimetric map. Gilbertsville Reservoir - Tennessee (1: 63420). Tennessee Valley Authority: Planimetric., 1938; 001553
    - Planimetric map. Gilbertsville Reservoir - Tennessee (1: 63420). Tennessee Valley Authority: Planimetric., 1938; 001554
  - Topographic Maps. Topographic Maps of Tenessee, a few including bordering states., 001054
    - Topographic map. Decatur County [TN] (1: 63420). Tennessee Geological Survey: County., 1918; 001545
    - Topographic map. Bath Springs, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001555
    - Topographic map. Chesnut Grove, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001556
    - Topographic map. Clifton 7.5, TN Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001557
    - Topographic map. Counce 7.5, TN Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001558
    - Topographic map. Daniels Landing, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001559
    - Topographic map. Eagle Creek, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001560
    - Topographic map. Hookers Bend, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001561
    - Topographic map. Huricane Mills, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001562
    - Topographic map. Hustburg, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001563
    - Topographic map. Jeannette, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001564
    - Topographic map. Leatherwood, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001565
    - Topographic map. Linden, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001566
    - Topographic map. Lobelville, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001567
    - Topographic map. Lowryville, TN-Al 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001568
    - Topographic map. Martins Mills, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001569
    - Topographic map. Olive Hill, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001570
    - Topographic map. Parsons, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001571
    - Topographic map. Perryville, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001572
    - Topographic map. Waynesboro, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001573
    - Topographic map. Wolf Pit Ridge, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001574
    - Topographic map. Pine View, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001575
    - Topographic map. Pickwick, TN-AL 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001576
    - Topographic map. Pittsburg Landing, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001577
    - Topographic map. Pope, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001579
    - Topographic map. Rockport, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001580
    - Topographic map. Savannah, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001581
    - Topographic map. Scotts Hills, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001582
    - Topographic map. Seventeen Creek, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001583
    - Topographic map. Sugar Tree, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001584
    - Topographic map. Thurman, TN 7.5 Quad. (1: 24000). U.S. Geological Survey: Topographic., 1937; 001585
- Photographs, Series II
  Black & White Photographs and negatives.
  - Specimens., 001057
    - Photographs & Negatives. Black and white negatives from Amsden's dissertation including Anthozoa Black and white negatives. ca 1949, 000610
    - Photographs & Negatives. Black and white negatives from Amsden's dissertation including brachiopods. Black and white negatives, 000608
    - Photographs & Negatives. Black and white negatives from Amsden's dissertation including crinoids, crystoids and blastoids Black and white negatives, 000609
- Miscellaneous, Series III
  - Field Notes. Copies if field notes and notebooks., 001058
    - Notebook. Field Notebook: Tennessee., 1942; 000147
    - Notebook. Field Notebook: Tennessee., 1942; 000148
    - Notes on Miser's Waynesboro Quadrangle: Tennessee., 1947; 000150
  - Locality Information., 001060
    - Locality information. Catalog of localities: Tennessee., 1947; 000149
  - Stratigraphic Sections., 001059
    - Stratigraphic sections: Tennessee., 1947; 000151
    - Stratigraphic sections: Tennessee., 1947; 000152